A Guide to the Opal David Papers 1933-1990
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Opal David Papers 1933-1990
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10971
2500 items
This collection consists of the personal and professional papers of Opal D. David (1906- ) of Albemarle County, Virginia, including correspondence, explanatory notes concerning the collection, articles, newsclippings, reports, speeches, campaign files, photographs, printed emphemera, transcripts, and political memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Ms. Opal D. David of Charlottesville, Virginia, on August 3, 1990.
Biographical/Historical Information
Opal David, an Albemarle County (Va.) politician, served as Democratic Party Committee chair, and was the first woman on the County Board of Supervisors. She also served as liason to the Planning Committee responsible for the County Comprehensive Plan, was member of the Virginia Commission on the Status of Women, and served as volunteer or consultant for numerous public service organizations.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the personal and professional papers of Opal D. David (1906- ) of Albemarle County, Virginia, and contains ca. 2500 items (10 Hollinger boxes, ca. 4 linear feet), 1933-1990, including correspondence, explanatory notes concerning the collection, articles, newsclippings, reports, speeches, campaign files, photographs, printed emphemera, transcripts, and political memorabilia.
Opal David was active in local issues and politics, women's issues, and education. The material in this collection concerns her work as the first woman on the Albemarle County Board of Supervisors, the chair of the County Democratic Committee, and liaison to the Planning Committee responsible for the County Comprehensive Plan; her participation in the Commission on the Education of Women (American Council on Education), the President's Commission on the Status of Women, and the Virginia Commission on the Status of Women; David's educational background, and other consulting work, government employment and voluntary activities.
Information on David's personal life and general career can be found in the following folders: biographical information, employment (2 folders), miscellaneous activities, and personal papers (2 folders). Mrs. David has also included explanatory notes on green sheets of paper concerning the collection. These have been placed in a folder at the beginning of Box 1.
David has several files pertaining to her work for the University of Virginia, including the working papers and report for the Self-Study done in 1962-1964; correspondence, working papers, first and second drafts of a report for a Twenty-Year Study initiated in 1967 but not used because of changes in the project design; and the Institute of Government Advisory Committee.
Files on local government issues in the miscellaneous topical series include those on Charlottesville Human Resources; Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation concerning annexation & revenue- sharing agreement, Buck Mountain Reservoir Site Agreement, the County Police Department, SAFE (Stop Annexation Forever); and the McIntire Public Library. Other files about local issues are located in the Albemarle County Board of Supervisors series and are chiefly concerned with the Comprehensive Plan for the County and the Zoning Ordinance.
Organization
This collection consists of two series, with each series' files arranged alphabetically by subject:
Series I: Miscellaneous Topical Files (Boxes 1-7)
Series II: Albemarle County Board of Supervisors
A. Issues (Boxes 7-9)
B. Campaign Files (Box 10)
Contents List
- Miscellaneous Topical Files 1933-1990 (Box 1-7)
  - Albemarle County Democratic Committee Chair 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education: Staffing Higher Education in Africa - Research & Report (UNESCO) 1962 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information 1945-1966 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Activity for Don Beyer 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Activity for David W. Carr - Supervisor 1977 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Activity - Miscellaneous 1975-1990 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Activity for Charlie Tolbert - Supervisor 1989 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Corporation: Overseas Educational Service 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Charlottesville Human Resources: Correspondence 1972-1976, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Charlottesville Human Resources: Related Reports and Studies 1972, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Charlottesville Human Resources: Report "Human Resources Planning and Organization" 1973 Jan (Box 2)
  - Charlottesville Human Resources: Working Papers 1972 (Box 2)
  - Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation: Annexation and Revenue-Sharing Agreement (1982) 1981-1984 (Box 2)
  - Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation: Annexation Newsclippings 1970-1990 (Box 2)
  - Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation: Buck Mountain Reservoir Site Agreement 1982 (Box 2)
  - Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation: County Police Department Campaign 1983 (Box 2)
  - Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation: General Meetings File 1982-1990 (Box 2)
  - Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation: League of Women Voters Educational Material re Annexation 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Citizens Committee for City-County Co-operation: SAFE Campaign (Stop Annexation Forever) 1982 (Box 2)
  - Civil Service Commission: Consulting Assignment 1967 (Box 2)
  - Commission on Local Government 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Commission on the Education of Women: Articles by Opal D. David 1959-1963 (Box 3)
  - Commission on the Education of Women: Backround & Reports 1957-1961 (Box 3)
  - Commission on the Education of Women: Continuing Contacts 1962-1981 (Box 3)
  - Commission on the Education of Women: Information and Research Notes - The Education of Women 1958-1961 (Box 3)
  - Commission on the Education of Women: Publications 1959-1961, 1963, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Commission on the Education of Women: Speeches and Addresses 1959-1963 (Box 3)
  - Commission on the Education of Women: Terminal Arrangements 1961 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Foreign Affairs Personnel 1962 (Box 4)
  - Employment (1930-1947) 1933-1946 (Box 4)
  - Employment (1947-1957) 1947-1956 (Box 4)
  - "Frivolous Writings" by Opal D. David 1937, 1977-1987 (Box 4)
  - Institute of Government Adivsory Committee 1981-1986 (Box 4)
  - Leadership Charlottesville (1983-1984) 1982-1986 (Box 4)
  - McIntire Public Library, Charlottesville (1963): Consulting Services w/ Library Board 1963 (Box 4)
  - McIntire Public Library, Charlottesville (1963): Drennan Report 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - McIntire Public Library, Charlottesville (1962 Summer): Management Survey & Report 1961-1965 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Activities 1976-1990, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Interviews and Letters to the Editor by Opal D. David 1976-1988 (Box 5)
  - National Broadcasting Corporation 1980 (Box 5)
  - Northwestern Virginia Health Systems Agency, Inc. (1977-1980) 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - Northwestern Virginia Health Systems Agency, Inc.: Diana Gray Resignation 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Personal Papers: Academic Transcripts 1937-1944 (Box 5)
  - Personal Papers: Applications for Civil Service Commission and the University of Virginia, etc. 1935-1986 (Box 5)
  - Piedmont 2000: A Community in Transition 1983 Mar (Box 5)
  - Political Memorabilia 1984-1990 (Box 5)
  - The President's Commission on the Status of Women: Education Subcommittee 1962-1963 (Box 6)
  - Sangamon State University: The Sangamon River Basin Citizen Planning Process 1980 (Box 6)
  - University of Virginia Hospital Advisory Committee 1983-1986 (Box 6)
  - University of Virginia: Self-Study 1963-1964, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - University of Virginia: Twenty-Year Study 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - University of Virginia: Twenty-Year Study - Report 1967, first draft (Box 6)
  - University of Virginia: Twenty-Year Study - Report 1968, second draft (Box 6)
  - Virginia Commission on the Status of Women Education Committee 1965-1967, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Virginia Commission on the Status of Women (1965-1967) Education Committee: Report 1965 Nov-Dec (Box 7)
- Albemarle County Board of Supervisors 1975-1979 (Box 7-9)
  - Issues
    - Administrative Decisions 1975-1977 (Box 7)
    - Comprehensive Plan: KDA, Inc. Working Memoranda and Opal David's Comments 1976-1977, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Comprehensive Plan Review Chronological File 1975-1978, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Comprehensive Plan Revision 1988 (Box 8)
    - Constituent Calls 1976-1977 (Box 8)
    - Grand Jury Investigation re T.M. Batchelor, Jr. 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Leaf Burning Ordinance 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Media Coverage 1976-1977 (Box 8)
    - Zoning Ordinance 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - Zoning Ordinance 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - Zoning Ordinance: Draft Proposal for Public Discussion & Hearing 1978 Nov 3 (Box 9)
    - Zoning Ordinance: KDA, Inc. Zoning Ordinance Revision 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Zoning Ordinance: League of Women Voters Land Use Committee 1975-1979 (Box 9)
    - Zoning Ordinance: Newsclippings 1979 (Box 9)
    - Zoning Ordinance: Proposed Ordinance for Albemarle County 1979 Jul 19 (Box 9)
    - Zoning Ordinance: Protective Zoning Around Rivanna Reservoir 1976-1978 (Box 9)
    - Zoning Ordinance: Revised 1977 (Box 9)
  - Campaign Files
    - Chronology 1975-1977 (Box 10)
    - Fund Raising 1975 (Box 10)
    - Issuances 1974-1975 (Box 10)
    - Issues - General 1975 (Box 10)
    - Jack Jouett Magisterial District Information 1975 (Box 10)
    - Letters to the Editor 1975 (Box 10)
    - Other Candidates 1975 (Box 10)
    - Record of Supervisor Stuart Carwile 1971-1977 (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook re the 1975 Election 1975 (Box 10)
    - Speeches, Statements, and Radio Spots 1975 (Box 10)
    - Steering Committee 1975 (Box 10)
    - Students 1975 (Box 10)
    - Tabloid Copy & Photographs 1975 (Box 10)
    - Workers & Volunteers 1975 (Box 10)
    - Campaign Materials 1975 (Oversize S-21)
    - "A Comprehensive Plan for the County of Albemarle 1971 (Oversize S-21)
    - Printed Material re the Comprehensive Plan for Albemarle County, Virginia 1977 (Oversize S-21)